This video is sponsored by Ground News.
Cars.
Cars are cool and interesting machines.
They come in lots of neat forms and
shapes, and they are fun to drive. They
are a great hobby and a useful tool to
get around where there is no good
alternative. So, cars are great. The
problem starts when they get to dominate
our lives. When all our public spaces
are given over to cars and we focus on
very expensive and wasteful car
infrastructure at the expense of
taxpayers money and physical space. When
cars make other ways of getting around
dangerous, like walking or biking for
fear of getting run over. When excessive
car use causes noise pollution, air
pollution, and recently with those xenon
headlights, light pollution. People
living in carcentric places also gain
weight more easily due to lack of
movement. And carentric residential
areas are generally less desirable
compared to their traditional
counterparts. Basically, the car is a
great servant but a terrible master. And
there is another surprising field where
this logic applies. Video games. with
Cyberpunk 2077 being an especially
egregious example. Why? How? What? Let's
take a look.
>> Wake the [__] up.
>> Cyberpunk 2077 is a shooter/ roleplaying
game sort of set in a corporatist
violent dystopian cyberpunk future. I
get it. where inequality, poverty, and
violence are rife, where cities are
composed of goaudy corporate skyscrapers
and walled off communities for the
wealthy, surrounded by various stages of
urban decay, ranging from somewhat okay
areas to highly dangerous slums. And all
of this is turbocharged via commonly
available cybernetic augmentations which
can improve human performance in various
ways with the side effect of turning
dangerous criminals into biomechanical
murder machines. Quite ironically, the
development of Cyberpunk 2077 was itself
reminiscent of a cyberpunk corporatist
future. Developers were overworked,
forced to do so-called crunch, which is
a games industry euphemism for abusing
employees with up to 65 to 80hour work
weeks without extra compensation. CD
Project Red, the developer of Cyberpunk
2077, was especially guilty of this
during the game's development. Employees
were forced to work 6 days a week for
more than a year, and I would imagine
those weren't 8-hour work days either.
The company later apologized, including
for calling the crunch not that bad, and
promised that from now on, the crunch
will be optional. A more humane approach
to crunch, which is like a more humane
approach to beating your kids. And
anyone who has ever worked in an office
environment knows that optional overtime
is optional in name only. Sure, you can
skip it, but if you do, guess what? From
then on, you'll just happen to get all
the bad assignments. You'll also miss
out on promotions. And whenever there is
layoffs, guess whose name is first on
the list? And surely enough, a year
later, it came out that crunching at CD
Project Red goes on all the same. And
for what? Let's talk about that after
the word from returning sponsor Ground
News. In any cyberpunk dystopia, being
wellinformed is essential. Ground News
achieves exactly that by being a news
aggregator website that collects
articles from around the world and gives
you an overview about different sources
takes on a given story, enabling you to
easily see a news sourc's political
bias, reliability, ownership, and more.
Ground news is a basic necessity even in
our world which is about to become a
cyberpunk dystopia itself. Let's take
the story about the Air Canada strikes
about employees defying a return to work
order and continuing to strike due to
low wages. Up here we can see the
summary of news stories from the left,
center, and right. Next to them is the
bias comparison tab highlighting the
focus and emphasis of each side.
Essentially your vibe check function.
Very highly useful engaging political
sites attitudes to a given topic. Here,
for example, the left focuses on
employees exploitation, while the right
takes an anti-employee stance with the
center sticking to passive reporting of
events. Ground news tells us that this
story was covered by 141 new sources at
the time of recording with a slight over
representation of left-leaning sources.
Further down, there is a neat visual
representation of sources and their
leanings in addition to factuality rates
and sources ownership structure. All the
information needed for a balanced media
diet. Ground News is a powerful
information tool helping you navigate
the news information landscape, enabling
you to stay on top of the news cycle. Go
to ground.news/adom
or scan this QR code to get 40% off the
ventage plan with unlimited access to
every feature. Or you can try their pro
plan for just $1 a month. Thank you for
checking out Ground News and thanks to
Ground News for sponsoring today's
video. Cyberpunk 2077, despite multiple
postponements, was a complete mess on
release. It was buggy, terribly
optimized, prone to crashes, and
generally the entire game felt
lackluster. A very basic, boring story,
a world that felt like an expensive
movie set instead of a living place,
role-play elements that didn't let you
roleplay, and a very shallow, unintive
take on the cyberpunk genre as a whole.
>> Pre-order now.
>> Bladeunner had you question what it
means to be human. whether androids
dream of electric sheep, if you will.
Ghost in the Shell had you consider a
world where the mind can be completely
detached from the body and the question
of how would a synthetically born
intelligence fit into all that? The
Matrix asks, "What if your reality was
just a simulation? And what if this
simulation was still the better option
compared to actual reality?" Psychopath
is set in a universe where a supercomput
scans people's brains and is able to
measure potential criminal tendencies.
and if it deems you to be too
potentially criminal, police will
apprehend you in advance. And then we
have Cyberpunk 2077 coming in with hot
takes such as corporations are bad. Then
it goes on to touch on deeper cyberpunk
themes, but doesn't do much with them,
which is pretty audacious if you think
about it. The game literally calls
itself Cyberpunk. It's like a game
called Ultimate Post-apocalyptic
Narrative RPG, and you boot it up and
it's Fallout 76. So, how come CD Project
Red's indentured servants couldn't come
up with a better story or even a theme
to explore? How come Cyberpunk 2077 was
so underwhelming compared even to the
more sober expectations? How come that
despite the insane amount of work going
into the game pushing developers to
their absolute limit with multiple long
delays even and the game costing almost
half a million dollar? How come that
after all that the game was still so
undercooked and rife with bugs? My hot
take, because of cars. Yep, you heard me
right. Let's compare a traditional 19th
century residential area to your average
21st century suburb. I'm going somewhere
with this, don't worry. The first thing
we notice is that the suburb needs far
more space to house the same amount of
people. Everything is farther away, and
having a car is absolutely necessary if
you want to get anywhere. In the
traditional area, stuff is close by. You
can get anywhere on foot or by bike,
except in Prague. Also, the buildings
around you from an enclosed space. If
you ever looked at photos of narrow
medieval streets, that cozy feeling you
get is because of that, at least in
large part. The buildings forming an
organic protective structure around you.
This also puts your brain more at ease
since it only has to process a small
segment of area at a time compared to a
large open area with single family homes
with a much wider field of view. And if
you want to get to a different area, you
usually don't have to walk or drive all
the way. You can just get on public
transit like a metro and be spat out at
your destination. Okay, so how does this
compute when it comes to Cyberpunk 2077?
Pun very much intended. Consider this.
Everything I just told you, the sense of
encloseness, the smaller field of view,
things being reachable on foot, areas
linked by set lines of public transit,
all of these also happen to be major
laborsaving methods in video game
design, and Cyberpunk 2077 did not
utilize any of them. Because of this,
Night City is basically a suburb
masquerading as an actual city. You need
a car to get basically anywhere unless
you want to stare at your character
walking for an hour. Now, following the
2.1 update in 2023, a metro system has
been added to the game. So, now you have
19 locations you can hop in between
without having to walk or drive. But
this was too little too late. Designing
Cyberpunk 2077 around cars had resulted
in a number of problems for game
developers. The first and biggest being
that they had to build an enormous map.
Cars are very mobile and as long as
there are no traffic jams in front of
you, you can get to places extremely
quickly compared to walking. Traffic in
Night City is deliberately set on low to
improve game performance and to not have
the players too in traffic jams. But
this also means that the city has to be
much much bigger. Otherwise, car rides
would take 10 seconds and the city would
feel tiny. And since the player is in
full control of the car most of the
time, you can't even take any design
shortcuts. Like in racing games where
the environment around the racetrack can
be far less detailed because players
just zoom past them. It's enough for a
town to simply appear like a town from
behind the wheel at high speeds obscured
by motion blur. In Cyberpunk 2077,
however, you must count with players
randomly getting out of their car and
walking around an area. Therefore, every
single street must always be maximally
detailed down to the net's ass. Even if
99.999%
of players will just zoom past an area,
never bothering to look at it, that
0.001%
might just decide to, and then make fun
of you for low detail assets. This alone
puts a colossal workload on your
developers, which led to the
affformentioned massive crunches at CD
Project Red, which then took away
precious development time from things
that actually matter, like a good story,
actual RPG features, performance
optimization, fixing the bugs, and so
on. Reliance on cars had forced
Cyberpunk developers to build out a 200
square kilometer map, much of it being a
very highly detailed urban area.
Something that jumps out at you
immediately is just how bad the car
controls are. Like it's just WD, then
there's the handbrake, but there's no
option like, you know, double tap W to
really step on the gas. So, I guess my
biggest gripe with Cyberpunk 2077 is
that like there's so much in here.
There's so much content in this game and
pretty much all of it is mediocre. Like
pretty much every single aspect of this
game feels just undercooked and
underdeveloped in various ways. The
shooting is mediocre. The vehicle
controls range from okay to terrible
depending on the person. The role
playing is [__] And then there are the
technical details where like stuff
really really falls apart. Like the
optimization is still terrible. Bugs
everywhere. The AI and the uh real-time
events are absolute [__] Like like
here, like what what's what's going on
here? Like there's some kind of random
shootout uh 200 m away from a police
checkpoint and then like nothing's
happening. The first car just like stops
and blocks the way as all the others are
trying to like ram their way out. Like
this does not look like a half a billion
dollar game. Yeah. And then I
accidentally bump into the police
checkpoint and they all open fire at me.
Nice. And it's it's [__] like this that
you keep encountering over and over and
over again in this game. And by the way,
I'm playing on patch 2.3. So we're like
half a decade of postrelease development
in and the game is still in such a
state. And the further problem is that
now you have to account for the player
having a two-tonon high velocity metal
tub that they can bring to most places.
So you either need to set car drop off
points to prevent the player from
parking in scripted locations or design
quest locations in a way that they are
separate and cannot be entered by car.
So now your game developers have to
spend their time and energy on
developing parking policy and
implementing transit model filters
instead of focusing on the actual game.
The core ccentric game world also causes
a metric ton of additional work with
developing traffic simulations, NPC car
and player car interactions, pedestrian
NPC on player core interactions, NPC
corn and pedestrian player interactions,
subsequent crowd mechanics, and so on.
These problems are individually solvable
for big developer teams. But if you take
them together, plus the need to design a
massive ultradetailed city, the end
result is overwork, constant delays, and
the game being stuck in development
hell. Then on release day, players are
treated to a buggy, undercooked,
unfinished mess that will need constant
post-release patching. All at a nearly
half a billion dollar price tag which
has only been increasing ever since. Is
it a bad game? No. But it's just it's
just mediocre. Like the game doesn't
have a highlight. It's like, "Oh, I play
Disco Alisium because of the incredible
pros, or I play Elden Ring because of
the beautiful world and the difficult
but very fun, you know, combat
mechanics, or I don't know, I play Death
Stranding because of the bonkers themes
it explores." And in Cyberpunk 2077,
there's just there's nothing like that.
Like, the game tries to mash so much
[__] together that like it can't really
focus on any of them properly at least,
and it just all falls apart. To give you
an idea of how massive this budget is,
DOSX Mankind Divided, a game very
similar in genre and theme, cost $50
million, about onetenth of the money
Cyberpunk must have burned through by
now. In large part because the game is
not carentric, which is wild, as the
game is set in Prague. And this enabled
developers to focus their efforts on
smaller areas instead of one enormous
city, cutting down the amount of work by
orders of magnitude. With that, let's
see if we can fix Cyberpunk 2077 by
fixing Night City itself, all the while
abiding by the Cyberpunk theme. We start
by taking the metro system as a basis.
It's 19 stops serving as the fastest
travel points between game locations. If
we need more, we just add more stops.
The areas the trains are going through
do not need to be fully designed. It's
enough to just put up a skybox around
the train to make it seem like you're
going through the city. The playable
area is always separated from
procedurally generated car traffic by
way of the former being under massive
elevated highways. This plays in nicely
with the cyberpunk theme. In particular,
this design is a staple of the 1995
Ghost in the Shell movie where most of
the action takes place in the narrow,
dark, moody under streets of Tokyo with
traffic rumbling far above on massive
elevated highways. And this design
immediately eliminates one of the major
development time syncs. You no longer
have to bother programming traffic
mechanics and vehicle behavior, at least
not that much and not that complex since
the player is not directly interacting
with them while on foot except in
specific scripted instances. Of course,
the player could drive a car later on on
the highways above. And since those
highways are elevated and separated from
everything else, the developers only
need to construct the building's facads
around them. They wouldn't actually need
to build out every single street
completely detailed. It's enough to make
the surroundings of the highways look
like a city at a glance since the player
will not be interacting with them up
close. And this would achieve two more
important things. Number one, the player
will actually really look forward to
owning and driving a car since yours
was, let's say, taken away. And now
you're blacklisted from driving or
something, and the biometric cameras
placed around the city would immediately
catch you while driving, and police
would lock you up until someone hacks
into the police databases or something
and removes you from the blacklist as a
reward for a quest or something. And
this unlocks a bunch of side quests and
mini games like illegal highway races,
high-speed deliveries on a timer and so
on. And this would actually be a really
fun bit of world building. You know,
large swats of the city are essentially
left behind by city leadership. There's
lawlessness and chaos except on the
highways, which is weirdly ordered and
regulated compared to the rest of the
city. All this would match the cyberpunk
theme beautifully. Cyberpunk worlds are
usually very right-wing. rampant
corporatism, societies segregated along
levels of wealth, mass poverty, comedic
levels of wealth inequality, everything
is privatized and so on. But
conservative societies also have a thing
for cars. In those societies, public
transit is viewed as some sort of
lowquality, filthy, dirty, last resort
option for the poor and minorities, for
those who cannot even afford a car. On
the other hand, cars are viewed as the
default method for transportation. And
being able to afford one is your ticket
to civilized society. And the bigger
your car is, the shinier and more
expensive it is, the more worth you are
perceived to have as a human being. So,
it would actually make a lot of
narrative sense for your character to
desire a car to be up there high above
the filth of the lower city, zooming
past the ghettos and slums in your shiny
automobile on the brightly lit, smooth,
squeaky clean highway compared to the
dark, filthy lower streets. I think this
would have been much better than just
giving you a car by default and then
having you slowly traverse these narrow
streets with a few cars on them at a
time. But basing the game's map design
on a metro system also enables something
extremely important. The shrinking of
the world map without it feeling any
smaller to the player. With appropriate
game design, even the smallest maps will
feel enormous. For example, Resident
Evil 2's playable map is comparatively
tiny. Yet, it feels absolutely enormous
due to a clever use of space and the
work you have to put in to actually get
to the end of it. So, in Cyberpunk 2077,
by having the player traverse the map on
foot, we could get away with much
smaller maps while potentially making
the game world feel even larger to the
player. Developers now only need to
fully build out a few streets next to
stations, which would be an enormous
reduction of their workload. They could
even layer the maps for more complexity.
Most locations could have extensive
underground parts, for example, in the
sewers, which is once again very fitting
of the cyberpunk theme, and are also way
faster to design and build, and it also
goes way easier on your GPU. I guess a
lot of people would not be okay with
shrinking Night City because oh, you
know, it's less cyberpunk. We have less
cyberpunk now. But that's like imagine
that we both like hamburgers, right? And
we can either go to this regular
restaurant where for like $10 you get a
burger, fries, and a drink. Or we can go
to this other restaurant where for $10
they take six Big Macs, they put them in
a big bowl, and they blend them down for
you into a paste, and then they spoon
feed it to you. And it's like in the
second case, you get technically more of
the thing that you like, but is that
really a positive in this case? So, I
believe that basing Cyberpunk 2077 on
Walking and Transit would have resulted
in a much better game where developers
would have had the time to implement
actual role- playinging elements and a
great memorable story instead of having
you play the exact same character except
with a different backstory that barely
influences anything. They could have
made the tutorial sequence an organic
part of the game instead of a random
simulation that interrupts your first
mission before it even starts. Or
somehow account for the fact that your
character, if choosing the corpo
background, will have personally
witnessed an assassination of public
officials shown to you live in your
boss's office who clearly and openly
admits that it was done by your
corporation.
>> You know what to do. Start now.
[Music]
Director Abernathy,
>> I watched the vote. What the hell was
that?
>> A deep clean after the [__] Frankfurt
dunked on us.
>> As we agreed, I got rid of the problem.
>> I told you to resolve the problem, not
massacre the European Space Council. Do
you understand what the cover up will
cost?
>> Your boss seems to be fully comfortable
with this, despite the cutthroat nature
of the corporate world and the
ubiquitous presence of recording
devices, including ones that might be
installed in your cybernetic
augmentations. But it doesn't matter
since all of this has absolutely no
impact on the rest of the game. The next
scene is you drinking champagne in your
boss's personal AV flying car that he
gave you to use only to have corporate
goons show up 5 minutes later and strip
you of your job position, money, and
even cybernetics.
>> DT policy's gone, Jack. So are my bio
controllers. Company pad. I mean they
have seized my bank account. Not frozen,
seized.
Glad to be that. Jack
just lost control of my life completely.
>> Which is quite jarring to say the least.
Like Jesus Christ, dude. Look, I know
what they were going for here. They
wanted to showcase the cruel, cutthroat
nature of the corporate world. But this
is just so hamfisted. It's like you
being friends with the US vice president
and you yourself are a highranking White
House official. And then one day the VP
is like, "Hey man, hey, check out this
recording of us assassinating [__]
Ursula on their lion." Yes, it was us.
This was done by us. We were the ones
responsible for this deed. Oh, by the
way, here are the keys to the
presidential limo. Go take it for a
spin. And then 5 minutes later, like two
FBI dudes show up and it's like, "Oh,
actually, you're homeless now." What?
This is how politics works. Like, come
on, man. But story aside, game mechanic
oversightes are often flatout
embarrassing. Like, nobody thought about
what happens if the player just climbs
on top of an NPC's car when it stops at
a red light. The game clearly has no
idea how to handle this and other cars
around you start bugging out with random
NPCs screaming and so on.
Don't do it.
Many of Cyberpunk 2077's failings are
due to an unfocused megalomaniac yet
shallow vision of what the game should
be, bloated beyond all proportions,
inflated by an incompetent leadership
who refused to accept that the project
needed some serious strategic
downscaling and instead proceeded to
crack the whip and forced their
employees to crunch for more than a
year. In some bizarre sense, CD Project
Red ended up becoming something of a
cyberpunk corporation itself, where
employees are just cogs in a machine
built to generate money from their
blood, sweat, and tears. I guess it just
really annoys me how people have a
really low standard for the media they
consume. And this especially applies
with video games, I feel like. And the
video game industry is especially guilty
of like being able to get away with
releasing unfinished [__] and people
thinking that it's okay. Like imagine if
Netflix came out with a series and it's
like oh you know it's full of actor
gaffs outtakes sound issues uh missing
special effects but that's okay. We're
going to release a new version in a year
and then it should be mostly done. Like
I'm sorry what? And it's like wow what a
hot take when you release something. It
should be done. And Cyberpunk after half
a decade of continuous patching post
release still feels like it's in late
beta. Like the game is not done.
Cyberpunk 2077 is the prime example of
less is more, and it could have been
achieved if the game was based on
transit and walking instead of cars. Or
at the very least, it could have gone a
long way in making it a much better game
than what it currently is.